so the pressure of restraint can
sometimes make the
Mind irrational so do you have any
advice for how
to maintain perspective in the face of
irrational mind uh well maintaining
perspective it's going to require you
losing perspective so to speak
maintaining perspective means developing
perspective so you can you can know what
the perspective is but when the rational
mind is pressuring you you're going to
lose it because otherwise you wouldn't
be pressured or not as pressured so
that's why it does boil down to them not
acting out of the irrational
mind and feeling that grain that's
trying to pull you with to go with it
and trying to then
exert the right perspective within
it so not like I need to get the right
perspective for this to go away more
like no no no this won't be going away
the only thing I can and should be doing
is have the perspective present with it
that's how eventually goes away so
really and that's not terribly hard to
do what's kind of hard to not forget is
to fall back into the expectation to for
this pain to go
away and then whether you're doing the
perspective or this or not acting out as
well you're doing it all under this uh
intention of so that it goes away and
that's why it's not going away you won't
go away because of that very reason so
it's like so it's then more
practically um it's better from a
practical point of view to then no no no
it's not about it going away I don't
want it to go away way I want it to stay
here so that I can present it with the
perspective and then keep it there for
as long as it's
there it's like a we said before like a
screaming child you can do this or that
to appease it so it stop screaming or
you could
just repeat how things are the actual
tell it that no this is how it is and it
refuses to hear that and continues to
scream and you just hold the picture in
front of it until it comes down and
accepts it
or the U the knocking of the door yeah
exactly hold on why am I bothered well
I'm bothered cuz I do still carry an
assumption that it shouldn't be
happening and it shouldn't be anybody in
front of my door because it would be
better if it's not so I want it to not
be in front of my door I like yeah but
that's not up to
you so the only reason you're resisting
or you're still pressured by somebody in
front of your door is cuz you still
carry expectation that I want to go away
from in front of my door I want front of
my door to be free and open it's like
but that's not your
domain what if
so cuz you start from this position of
ignorance and you're just
like sometimes even like not aware maybe
that you are like s
I don't know opening the door somehow
without
well no no reason to mystify it like
that there always even if it's true to
some extent it's irrelevant really
what's relevant is the stuff that you
are aware of yes then later on you might
find oh there are those other subtler
ways but to assume the subtler ways now
are responsible for this they're not
they're not it's what you're doing now
are you now still
carrying the heavy something you no I
refuse to live under this I want it to
go away from the front of my door I
don't want it to be there that's really
the problem so
problem so
it's the whole training that boils down
to maintaining the perspective or
presenting the perspective or reminding
yourself of the right perspective in
face of that pain that has arisen on
account of of that irrational
pressure could you say that you'd be
holding up that picture to the
child but you know it's not for the
child you know the child could scream
forever but it's for you to remember as
well well it's for you to remember for
sure but fundamentally it's so that the
child eventually learns yeah so like you
can't help but want pain to go away yeah
but you can certainly make sure that
it's not the the root of your immediate
intention like but I want it now
whatever I do I want like yeah you
practice because you want to be free
from suffering yeah but not in that
sense of through that denial but through
the sense of no no no I will be free
from suffering when the Mind stops or
loses the ability to become irrational
and turn against me and itself
but you could say you could like um if
you practice this for a while so you're
not acting
out and then pressure comes and goes
sometimes more sometimes less sometimes
better sometimes worse but overall
you're not sliding back in terms of your
UNH wholesome actions you're not going
against the precepts you're not losing
sense restraint um as I said sometimes you
restraint um as I said sometimes you
more accurately reestablish perspective
sometimes that's just feel like too much
work and you just weathering it until it
stops um you have to go to some extent
of that it's
inevitable but as you're doing it as I
said even if you're just not acting out
but even if you don't have any
perspective at the time it's still
obviously a form of staying with it so
it's not like oh this is wrong now no
there is no wrong for as long as you
don't act out of it as long as the door
is not open there is nothing wrong what
you do inside yes it's not the best
thing you should do but it's nowhere
near the threshold of it's
wrong cuz that's another trick to get
you to open the door well it's wrong I
might as well open the door
now but for as long as the door is not
open is is is no it's not wrong it's not
wrong it simp isn't cannot be no matter
how much it doesn't matter how how
confused how doubtful how everything
else you might be feeling it's like yeah
but it door's not
open so it's still better than being
open so it's still more right
then it would have been
otherwise is is that the
clarity about what that doorway is always
about what that doorway is always
available well whenever there is a
pressure there's a
doorway like the the line of because you
can lose sight of that yeah right yeah
um but
yeah the recollection that it's I think
let's say the doorway is basically if
you if you like really act out of
it so you could be walking towards the
door be on the other side of the door
but not open it obviously if you're
constantly just sitting on the other
side of the door next to the door handle
well the pressure to open it will
increase so you need to recognize that
as well but fundamentally as long as you
don't open it you are safe even if he
doesn't feel like
that and he won't feel like that because
that's the only true
safety that's why the mod would
presented as no no no this is the worst
thing you can do don't do
this but you could that's and that's the
on that part when you're on the
inside of the house when you're not
opening the door
but you are kind of getting like walking
past the the door examining the door
thinking about opening the door trying
to all this you realize okay I could
stop that now and that's that part we
talked about before of like U not
allowing images to take the center
stage and as we said also I think he
wanted the talks it's
like even without them being the center
stage you already know what they
are so even if I don't explicitly start
thinking about things I'm being
pressured and all this and that if I
were to allow it I know exactly what I
will think so it's like so I I won I
won't allow them to send stage again I'm
not trying to get rid of who is in front
of the door I'm not trying to get rid of
all these thoughts that are that would
be associated with it I'm just keeping
them into that blur I'm not allowing
them to crystallize through my own
efforts if they pop up on their own
that's fine that's a completely
different thing than if they pop up
because I intended them to do so
although it feels the same the end
result feels was the same it's the same
image that popped up but one came
through your own intention one didn't if
it's through your own intention that's
the center stage I talk
about and and that's actually there's a
whole whole Universal difference between
the two but you need to arrive at
it the difference is internal it's not
in the content of the image and and the
center stage that's remain the same but
it's how it got there means whether
there is the five Aggregates with upana
or without
or or they would and eventually if if
you do not allow the center stage there
will be no five Aggregates there will be
the complete sensation of anything that
was
activated it's like that I don't know if
I said it in some talk or just when we
were speaking without recording it's
like you imagine you have like a like a
like a I don't know a
place with a glass in between but it's
just like a I don't know square meter of
foot space and there is like a
transparent glass in between so it's
like the on the same
spot but the only way to get from one
side of that
glass like 10 cm well not even 10 like
one cm on the other side of the glass
you have to go all the way around
completely all the way around through a
different world to arrive at the same
thing it looks the you still look at the
same thing that's there on that
floor and that's that's this that's
exactly it so you have the Imes and
stuff that present themselves Andre mind
wouldn't see a difference between
picking them up with your
intention and then coming up on their
own and then you would think I need to
deal with the content I need to deal
with the thoughts themselves it's like
no you need to deal with your
intention in thinking them and that's
that practice of not allowing them to
center stage while the blurry cloud is
there waiting to crystallize but if it
crystallizes on its own you're free
you're still free
you are Untouched by it if it
crystallizes through your own intention
of picking it up that's what touches
you and that's a practice that can only
be done indoors you can only do this
practice and eventually discern this
difference if the door remains
closed if you go out to deal with stuff
that's in front of your door through
your techniques and managements and
stuff none of this will be applicable
this domain ceases to exist
the distinction between those two well
the distinction theoretically remains
but practical possibility of seeing it
is U gone because you need to close the
door for those distinctions to start to
appear it's like so imagine now say you
are not
your your there's a hindrance pressure
in you whether it's the doubt ill will
sensuality you know the state of mind
you know the general Cloud that's
waiting there pressuring you to start
intentionally crystallizing the
thoughts so if you refrain again I don't
need to be cancel in the mind that's the
painful part when you think you need to
be changing this this weight in the
direction of this weather and that's
impossible but you actually I don't know
have to do that the sole reason that any
of that will be a problem is if I'm
making a connection creating a
connection activation through
intentionally crystallizing thoughts
that are being pushed at
me so if you are not allowing them to
Center Stage say there is a mind that
pressures you towards I don't know
thoughts of
will somebody annoys you if you were to
intentionally now go towards those
thoughts you know exactly what you you
will think but you're not doing that so
the pressure is there but there is no
specific thoughts of hatred that come
from you what are you left with there
and then like in your state like even
imagine now whatever subtle pressure you
might be feeling on kind of some
hindrance you're not allowing the center
stage in regard to that very pressure
what are you left with then
now the pressure B yeah of course the
pressure is there but broadly speaking I
mean your body just basically here and
now yeah you're left with here and now
so you're not and that here and now
there it's not being thought through a
taken up pressure it's what you're left
with by not allowing the intentions to
take up the pressure and if you start
like thinking it as a way to yeah I was
going to say that and that's why like
sometimes people then think aha so I'll
think here and now to not ex the
pressure he like but that's now your
pressure so although it's the same here
and now you arrived at it completely
from the opposite
directions the here and now that you
often hear about it's like you focus you
get to it you get to it you get to it
it's like no the here and now is what
you are left with and you could see how
it was maybe right at some point to some
degree with somebody they arrived at it
rightly and then they mystify the here
and now and then subsequently as that
has been repeated thousands of times
people forgot the whole context of the
actual travel and journey to it right
one and then they just start no just
here and now nibana is already here
there's nothing to do just focus on it
just stop this just just just kind of be
present and all of that and it's like
what I said it's like you you remain on
this sheet of glass because the other
one the other side remains identical
looks identical so you see no difference
but there is a difference whether you
are in left with here and now through
your concentration practice of being
here and now or through simply not
allowing the crystallization of the
pressuring
thoughts free restraint yeah so here and
now is the result it's not something you
do it's the result of something you
do and you can't just through a shortcut
just focus on here and now and bypass
the work because that will be taken up in
work because that will be taken up in
the same
way so you might it might be
um I don't know simultaneous with you
asking a question like at the right time
and then to regain perspective mhm and
then you latch on to that asking of
question and that becomes your method
your method yeah you just start doing it
blindly yeah and you don't see that it
was just
the yeah it's inevitable like you will
be doing it to a degree it's not going
to be perfect the right the first time
but that's why the instruction has to
remain unobscured and keep pointing you
and you keep reminding yourself of where
the actual emphasis and the right work
is so you start you ask a question at
the right time you establish the
perspective you don't C you don't allow
the the pressuring you know peripheral
cloud of thoughts to crystallize through
your own uh ignorant efforts but then
you slip you get coordinate but then
when you catch yourself that that's what
you've been doing you know like okay but
now that needs to be included rightly
now in regard to that I don't repeat the
same mistake or I try to like foresee it
mistake or I try to like foresee it
before it's before I allow
it and that's how you progress but if
you catch yourself and then you think oh
but this is actually not a problem
that's it that's why the wrong view is
the worst possible thing a person can
do like even from the samsara point of
view because for that sole reason you
want stay on the right level you won't
endure the pressure U somebody in front
of your door on the right level cuz you
would think you don't have
to and that's another thing see you have
somebody pressuring you to open the
door you've been panicking inside and
moving and getting closer or going away
or trying to cement the door or freaking
throw a bomb outside what doesn't matter
and then eventually you sort of come
down cuz you recognize yeah it's still
but the point is the door is not open so
why don't I calm down these thoughts
while I'm inside and you calm them down
again not through denial not through
wishing there's nobody in front of the
door just just let me not have that last
say in their crystallization just keep
my mind free from those images in the
center stage while they're there how do
you know they're there well allow the
sent stage you know exactly what's going
to come even before it comes so you know
they're there you know what they are
already even without thinking them
explicitly and then you realize you do
that and then the pressure cannot touch
you then you can have hundred many
people in front of the door or creatures
trying to press you to open it the only
reason you pressure it is when those
images were taken the center stage
through your own ignorant intention of
placing them
there that's why aran's behavior is
there is
no measurable even perceivable
difference between private and
public it's the same
as in private he's so in public as in
public he's in private there is no
there's no change
there but to go back to his
example let's say um there's a
question but it's is the case that in
that moment there is a sense of anxiety
mhm and there is a sense of
um maybe like obligation or yeah that
that I need to ask a question right
now
that yeah opening the door is to act out
of that to to to to ignore that or but
that's a I mean not yeah not quite it's
kind of coming to the door handle and
and but it's it wouldn't really be
opening the door opening the door is
when you act cuz the pressure the
hindrances are not going to pressure you
towards learning more about the dhama or
something your desperate efforts might
go in that direction because you still
try to get rid of who's in front of the
door but fundamentally opening the door
is you know when you act towards the
pressures when you really give in so as
I said as long as that's not done you're
still safe but then yes of course once
you become confident in that you could
realize yeah but I don't even have to
think about the
door it's not a problem I don't even
have to think about who's in front of
the door that's not a problem the only
problem is that I'm pressure here and
now through intentionally through
ignorant intentions allowing those
images associated with it to take the
Cent stage again it's kind of it sounds like
stage again it's kind of it sounds like
it can easily become on that level it's
like oh I asked the question I acted out
of it didn't I I made a it's it's
mistake like no you haven't you're still
inside the door is still closed you
haven't acted out you haven't acted out
of the major doubt and abandoned the
training you haven't acted out on
account of the hindrance of sensuality
and broke the preets you haven't acted
out on a account of anger and punched
somebody or said something really like
Furious you
haven't yes mentally I've been getting
to the door and wanting to do it or not
or that's the
training oh yeah and I've been asking
these stupid questions this whole time
just really that's the training then you
get to recognize that it's like okay now
I refine it within the indoor
environment that's the point there is
still no opening of the
door but it's not incidental the mar
wants to confuse you about what you do
inside so that then makes no difference
whether the door is open or not because
that's how it's going to
feel because there is a huge difference
whether the door is open or
not I was going to say like
cuz
it's acting out doesn't mean doing some
action while there is a pressuring state
of mind because you have you're going to
be doing something while there is a
pressuring state of mind it's whether
what you're doing is like really rooted
in that pressuring State of Mind as in
like what it wants you to
do opening the door even within that
yeah even within
that in the beginning it will be like
the asking question might be rooted in
the pressuring state of
mind let's see it's still not on the
level of opening the
door for what you're obviously pressure
towards so it's going to be rooted like
you pacing inside of your of of the of
the of of the room with the door closed
and coming close to the door and walking
away it's all determined by the pressure
at the outside of the door so I'll just
stop it well that will now be determined
by the stuff that's in front of your
door I'll just sit still motionless why
because there is a pressure that I'm
under because somebody's in front of my
door trying to make me to open it
whatever you do will be rooted in it but
it's like you recognize
okay by not allowing it to spill out
it's still contained and that's the
training now once it's contained and
there is a difference between that
because as I said the whole point of
Mara making confused is so you see that
there is no do you think there is no
difference I'm confused in here I might
be confused it doesn't matter I might
open the door it's like no no no it's
still a better type of confusion it's
better type of pain and that's what
would I said you should replace the
happiness of household life with the
happiness of
anunciation the happiness of outdoor
projects with the happiness of indoor
peace the uh you should replace the pain
of the outdoor engagements with the pain
of indoor
pressure and then eventually you would
abandon that too
is that also is there something um
relevant there as well about basically
kind of
prioritizing I suppose like doing things
in the right order
um in terms of um like prioritizing the
the things that you are
about um rather than trying to for
example like you were talking about once
you're inside the the door door and you
can start like not um not allowing the
images to crystallize you know so that
you don't even have to do that part and
then you can be at peace and you know
from the point of VI of somebody who's
like still fully very much pressured
it's like oh that sounds very nice let
me quickly try and do that part so still
not have to deal with it and actually
that won't work you know it's no and you
feel it it doesn't work but right
information remains there to be
eventually to land on a right thing if
you keep doing it that's the
point that's the point but no definitely
there is there is a
whole sequence to this because you could
be trying to not allow the center stage
while your door is freaking wide open
and things just coming in and out
doesn't matter actions speech doesn't
matter like yeah you're just revolving
around abstract ideas
is even if you had the right instruction
so it's like no the training is you got
to
learn like for the door to remain
closed and
then take on that it's going to feel
pressuring now cuz before you used to
roam around whatever you wanted it's
like yeah but that's why you were pray
to suffering wherever you
went is it is it
also it's not just like well today the
door was
closed this week the door was closed
it's just it's like yeah it needs to
stay closed yeah it needs to St and it's
not like I do it now and then later yeah
like I do it now and then later yeah
I'll close it for the you know five days
open it on the weekends or something
yeah I mean I suppose if somebody's
absolutely wild assuta
unrestrained it's could be a way to
start to eventually have your doors
closed all the time but you got to
recognize that that's nowhere near the
necessary threshold for any successful
practice but yes some people need to
work towards the
threshold but it's it's important to
qualify this because if you say well yes
start by having your door closed three
or four days they'll think okay by doing
this absolute subpar levels I am also
practicing the dhama no you're just
getting closer to the level where you
could start practicing the dhama which
of course you could argue it's a form of
practice but it's not a dam practice
it's like Preparatory practice
practice I've been
um
thinking kind of maybe a rough marker
just to kind
of kind of
gauge to gauge where you're at would be
um yeah what what what you're still
opening actually opening the door too
yeah um like your like your work the
sort of worst moment in sense um what
still getting what well yeah and then so
you might say like you're not opening
the door but you're still peeking
through the curtains yeah yeah so it's
like oh hold on but that means I'm still
concerned yeah I'm still pressured by
the outside so I'm still acting towards
it then you might not be peeking through
the curtains but as I said you still
come and you just just just think about
pressing the handle even if you know
you're not going to do it it's like yeah
well why am I doing even that so that's
that refinement of the purification of
your thoughts and then as I said if you
go in that direction
the distinction that I said between
thoughts just popping up on their own in
the center stage and thoughts being
placed in the center stage through your
own ignorant intention it's the
difference between samsara and Iana
basically nothing else it's like the the
root of all the problems
and clarifying that or clarifying this
as well just like the door what act what
counts is acting out the doorway and so
on it's done
practically no other way yeah no other
way and yes from the point of view of
and yes from the point of view of
eventually not being moved by any
pressure um when you think back pacing
inside of the room on account of the
pressure was acting out but it wasn't
acting out acting
out yes like say if you you're pressure
so you got you there anger knocking at
the door and you don't open it you're
clear about it and then you start to
you're just enduring
that and it's still and just told this
pain well I'll
just keep knowing that it's at the door
examine it discern it and then the
thought well you just acted out there
yeah your discernment is doing something
isn't it but that's it is doing
something it is doing something it's a
doing of it's discernment of just
reinforcing the fact that door is closed
it's it's the simile of the purifying
purifying of the gold in the sutas you
know when you're purifying when you're
separating the co
impurities from the liquid
mass when you put aside the stuff you
want to keep you take lots of impurities
with it just not as
course then when you start purifying
that you put further aside stuff you
want to keep it still contains all the
impurities so technically you are still
acting out you are still taking on other
impurities yeah but at the expense of
dropping a coarser one cuz you can't be
as I said before like with a tweezer
picking microscopic impurities in the
gold what is like lump of excrement
floating around it's just well that's
like makes absolutely no
difference so the problem is not like oh
I acted out I ask the question and I
like this the problem is then whether
you have perspective in regard to
that so like yeah but the door is not
open it's not ideal sure but now I get
perspective I recognize that and there's
already confidence born from it okay so
I can think about it even if it's out of
pressure cuz I'm not going towards the
door and I'm not thinking in terms of
opening the
door then eventually but why am I even
thinking about it in that sense why am I
even allowing Center Stage for those
thoughts to come forward when I already
know the answer it's just a compulsion a
pressure to to allow it to to to place
itself to crystallize itself so I won't
do even
that and that's all you know you know
even from the start you know when
somebody shuts the door by taking on a
life of the eight
precepts and they finally shut that door
but then they they they hold it
shut every second of the life they're
leaning into the door and squeezing the
handle so that it's not
opened and it's like yeah you might
start like that and probably many people
would but then you recognize hold on I
don't need to hold it because it can't
be opened on its own
the only way for that door to open
cannot be be open accidentally not open
from the outside the only way to open it
is me to actively open it so you don't
need to keep the precepts you just need
to not break
them but that in itself will cause doubt
they will then blur the line where the
door is and if people even allow people
that are still dependent on gripping the
door out of
fear and feeling justified in doing so
if you tell them you got to let go of
the door for them that's like saying you
have to open it and go and dance with
what's in front of the door like there
is no
difference and that's why they'll
continue clutching into the door which
is the whole essence of s by the P
mus you don't know how to relax you
relax you don't have to injure
ComEd well yeah you don't know like you
don't know where the where the problem
is where the problem actually comes from
because what happens if you let go of
the door your mind gets filled with a
doubt what if that door opens on its
own and it's like that's your practice
now that's your
training developing your mind yourself
in regard to the mind of doubt that's
why Sil parasa and the doubt go hand in
hand so by then accepting that the
training is on the level of
Doubt developing your mind in regard to
doubt not acting out of it enduring on
the right level not allowing
intentionally thoughts to crystallize
that they rooted in it all of that see
in order to accept that you need to
abandon your previous Notions of the
training being holding the door as
tightly as possible and doing magical
visualizations they will they somehow
miraculously remove the pressure from
the front of my door one day just won't
be
there and you realize oh yeah there
people don't do the right practice
because they refuse to give up the wrong
practice Yeah but you you've already
opened the door because of fear so so
you actually on the other side holding
well I mean yeah in a way the door is
not open but another way you not you're
yeah you're you're not really developing
anything in inside because you're still
very much concerned with the outside as
in like the thing is if you were to stop
holding it the problem is you'd just be
opening it you don't see any you would
open that's not holding the door means
open opening it yeah so it's a lot of
pressure you don't open it and then you
don't even want to look you don't even
know about what's outside there because
that's so you
just wish wish for it to go away yeah
you just shut down try to shut
everything or just get into meditation
techniques yeah just to
ignore you don't so you still don't want
to train no possibility so you still
don't want to train in regard to the
existing pressure you still want it to
Simply go away not be there you know if
you're sitting in your room and you have
this whatever pressuring TOs and now
it's like okay let me just go for a walk
to calm down or something and then
that's acting out pressure that's acting
out of pressure no you can go for a walk
and or you can well it is you could say
it is acting out of pressure it but
again not to the extent of opening the
door yeah exctly that's what I mean by
allowing that by recognizing that you
are kind of at the same time seeing the
difference yeah yeah but by just
doubling down now and saying oh that's
pressure no no no no not to everything
automatically it's like that wishing
that self cancellation on the inside so
then then see I can either cancel the
problem outside of the door or wish for
it or cancel me inside either way that's
the presumed kind of pathway of
resolution which is sensuality and
self-mortification in it in its
principle so it's like yeah there is
pressure I'm going for a walk or I'm
doing this or that but I know for sure I
recognize it there is no confusion in
regard to to what extent that goes and
yes ideally I don't want to be moved
even to that extent but in order to
arrive there I first have to get used to
this extent yeah so go for walk every
day if it maintains you not opening the
door if it allows you to stay with the
pressure if it enables you to not allow
through the ignorant intention
crystallization of the images concerned
with the outside with sensuality with
ill will with acting out on that level
so it's like yeah I'll go for a walk and
perspective remains eventually as I said when you
remains eventually as I said when you
get used to
that going for a walk will become too
course you won't even have to do
that Al maybe like whatever you do
inside is like highlighting the
actual door that you're not opening that
that practice you know that the practice that
practice you know that the practice that
is important the core practice of not
opening the door whatever you do inside
highlights that yeah yeah as a I got to
do something well let me just highlight
the thing that I shouldn't be doing yeah
as long as it's not that basically
that's like what is what determines
whatever you else you can do as long as
it's not that and and it's going to be
as I said before it's going to be
sometimes it will be more obvious
sometimes less but that's training and
also the point is then to which
obviously as I said with the right
instruction hopefully you won't fall
into a wrong view of then thinking okay
going for a walk is the practice by
magically going for a walk pressure will
resolve itself it's like no these are
something you do on account of uh being
pressured by not acting out to the full
extent but not being able to remain
unmoved either so you still know where
the practice is where the training is
you just as I said when purify the gold
you have to for a while put aside gold
with the other impurities and can't
possibly be concerned with everything
all at once because that will make you
lose sight of the obvious impurities
that you should have could have easily
abandoned because that's that's exactly
the pathway people would take aha close
the door pressure builds up I want to
ask question that's do pressure
shouldn't do it and then end up becoming
no no no no I was no well I didn't even
no doesn't matter just just absolute
denial no no no no no no but then it's
like but why are you saying yes to that
then mhm so it becomes very limiting and very
mhm so it becomes very limiting and very
as I said completely unnecessary as well
and if it happens when you catch it then
it's that's when you recognize how much
you learned and whether your perspective
is informed or
not cuz you know people would arrive
it's like oh well no to everything makes
no difference what I do that would be
the next jump into conclusion because
you've been saying no trying to deny
stuff on account kind of the pressure
they then LED you to a view that it
doesn't matter what you do it's all the
same anyway it's like but that's not
quite true isn't
it and even if we take it for the sake
of an argument to be true what you do
then if it doesn't matter what you do
why is then your next course of action
going to open the
door it doesn't matter what you do so
why don't you just keep it closed oh it
doesn't matter what I do thus I'll go
back outside that's usually what it
leads to self-mortification it has to
just revert you back all the way where
you started what you shunned the bait
that you try to avoid and not learn
about or feel pressured about ran on top
of a mountain like a deer her did
starved out and then just went back
straight not knowing the difference
between what's the bait what the
threshold is and where the door handle
is so you could dive
into it's not really sensor strength
it's like a sense deprivation I guess
but um or like take
on austerities which are particular
which are unnecessary for that uh for
what you're actually able to
withstand but then but you but you are
holding them so do you learn within that
them so do you learn within that
container or you're holding what like
the austerities te technically the
deprivations yeah technically no you
wouldn't learn anything no cuz you're
looking completely in a in a wrong place
even as I said you're emulating the
right thing m
seemingly uh internally it's done for
completely different
reasons no and yeah that's that's a good
point the difference between sense
restraint sense restraint is not
deprivation sense restraint is saying no
to the right things to the extent that
the pressure arises and then train in
regard to the pressure not shy away from
it not try to deny it deprivation it's a
view of if I say no to things pressure
won't touch me if I just blindly
increase things I deny I will be free
from the mental pressure and that's as
ignorable as engaging with sensuality as
the word
say if I'm still tou pressure just means
I must increase the D down just saying
no to more things more things that's
what's missing
no had always been curious about this
step from virtue and sensor like it's
kind of often just said like virtue and
sens like they're kind of simultaneous
or like
uh but no no yeah it's quite clear I
think that
virtue there's a reason why it's well
sense restraint involves
intention like the sense straint in the
sutas it's not on the level of just
saying no so it's like the mon doesn't
look at the site that's provocative of
last there and then which means it can
be a different thing at different
times sometimes the same thing might not
be provoking lust that might not be the
intention while you're looking at it
so but if you just adopt the view that
you know the thing is judged by its
content that's why I must say no to it I
mean some things are obvious always un
wholesome and that's kind of what virtue
addresses things you don't do but the
training in sense restraint is a lot
more Nuance than just say no to anything
you want to see it's like no it's why I
want to see
it why the eyes go this way why thees Z
want to and it's like oh now yeah I know
that it's rooted in sensuality in
pleasure or distraction I say no to
it but it can be the same thing that
then it's not rooted then you don't say
no to it oh but it's still good to say
no to it no it's not saying no to it
when you shouldn't obscures the
Mind removes the basis for training
there and then so it's like so why are
you doing it then are you doing it to
train the mind or you doing it to
fulfill some projected um ideal of
austerity and Purity that's obviously
very ignorant the difference between
thoughts taken the center stage on their
which is basically not the center stage
and thoughts taking the center stage
through your own allowance is the
difference in your intention nothing
else do have intention to not allow them
to crystallize or do I intention that
allows them to
crystallize but you know if you're not
if you have not been training in regard
to corser forms of your own intention
this Discerning them seeing them be
pressured by them endure them not acting
out of them it's like you're not going
to see this it will make no difference
it will sound like be here now
just focus on the present moment you're
not going to see the whole trajectory to
travel in
between all around